<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian ministry of the Church of England vindicated and distinguished from the antichristian ministry of the Quakers containing a brief reply to a false and foolish libel stiled A letter to the clergy of the diocess of Norfolk and Suffolk, &amp;c., by a nameless author ... wherein his folly is detected, his lies confuted ... / by a member of the Church of England, Francis Bugg.</title>
            <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30024</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5369</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35451</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15313183</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15313183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103405</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30024)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103405)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1146:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian ministry of the Church of England vindicated and distinguished from the antichristian ministry of the Quakers containing a brief reply to a false and foolish libel stiled A letter to the clergy of the diocess of Norfolk and Suffolk, &amp;c., by a nameless author ... wherein his folly is detected, his lies confuted ... / by a member of the Church of England, Francis Bugg.</title>
                  <author>Bugg, Francis, 1640-1724?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by J. Robinson ... and H. Rhodes ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Letter to the clergy of the diocess of Norfolk and Suffolk, &amp;c.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103405:1"/>
            <p>THE Chriſtian Miniſtry OF THE Church of <hi>ENGLAND</hi> Vindicated and Diſtinguiſhed FROM THE Antichriſtian Miniſtry OF THE <hi>QUAKERS.</hi> CONTAINING A Brief Reply to a Falſe and Fooliſh Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, ſtiled, <hi>A Letter to the Clergy of the Dioceſs of</hi> Norfolk <hi>and</hi> Suffolk, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by a Nameleſs Author, yet a pretended Member of the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> WHEREIN His Folly is Detected; His Lies Confuted; His Weakneſs Diſcovered; and his Malice Reproved. By a Member of the Church of <hi>England, FRANCIS BUGG.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>That we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every Wind of Doctrine, by the Slights of Men, and cunning Craftineſs, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they lye in wait to deceive. <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 4.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author: And are to be ſold by <hi>J. Robinſon</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Lion</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. And <hi>H. Rhodes</hi> at the <hi>Star</hi> in <hi>Fleet-street.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:103405:2"/>
            <head>Advertiſement.</head>
            <p>WHereas the Sheet, intituled, <hi>A Letter to the Clergy, &amp;c.</hi> is to my certain Knowledge u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally ſpread in <hi>Oxford, Wickham, Ipſwich, Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Bury, Cambridge, Norwich, Lyme, Ely,</hi> and divers other Parts of the Nation, to the great Scandal of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and given <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> (they having a common Bank for that and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch Purpoſe) into the Hands of Gentlemen, Tradeſmen, Inn-keepers, Hoſtlers, and others, to the great Prejudice of common Chriſtianity, and is a cunning Stratagem, deviſed, and ſet on foot by the Arch Emiſſaries of <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> under the Vizor of a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whilſt there is great Reaſon to believe him to be a real <hi>Quaker;</hi> whoſe Principle and Practice hath been to Lie, Diſſemble, Forge, and Subſcribe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Conſent of the Parties, as <hi>Anne Docwra,</hi> (a Member of that Schiſm, and now in their Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and a Writer and Defender of their Hereſie) hath ſhewed. Theſe are therefore to give notice, That any Perſons, zealous for our Holy Religion, may have this Book ready ſtitcht for 2d. <hi>per</hi> Book, if they will buy 25, 50, or 100 together, at Mr. <hi>Janeway</hi>'s, Book-binder, next Door to <hi>Child</hi>'s Coffee-Houſe in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, <hi>London,</hi> In order to a Univerſal Diſcovery of this Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrodite in Religion, who lies ſculking behind the Curtain, ſtinging like a Serpent; whoſe Throat is an open Sepulchre, whoſe Mouth muſt be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and Folly manifeſted, leaſt the uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Triumph over the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:103405:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Apoſtle, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> writing to the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> gives them many Precepts, and ſound Exhortations, in order to the building them up in their moſt holy Faith; amongſt which, this to me ſeems not the leaſt, <hi>cap. 4. v. 14. That we henceforth be no more Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every Wind of Doctrine, by the Slights of Men, and cunning Craftineſs, whereby they lye in wait to deceive.</hi> Again, writing to his Son <hi>Timothy,</hi> he ſeems to Inculcate the ſame over again, foretelling what ſhould come to paſs. <hi>2 Tim. 3.13. But evil Men and Seducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived.</hi> It's true, no Man can deceive another, but he deceives himſelf; yet ſuch is the Influence, that Intereſt, and the Love of the World, have upon the depraved Nature, and ambitious Deſire of ſome Men, that they will uſe all the Slights and cunning Craftineſs they can, to deceive others: And when one Engine will not do, they'll try another, as we ſee by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who by their Slights and cunning Craft, have deceived Thouſands, under the Pretence of their Seeming Sanctity, and Pharaſaical De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mureneſs, as well as by their Books, which they generally pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be given forth by the Holy Ghoſt, from the Mouth of the Lord, and by the moving of the Eternal Spirit, and as ſuch, to be of greater Authority than the Bible, as <hi>G. White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> teaches in his Book, <hi>Truth defending the Quakers,</hi> p. <hi>7.</hi> And thereupon they read their Epiſtles thus wrote, in their Meetings, as the Word of God, whilſt they never read one Chapter of the Bible in their Meetings: I ſay, by theſe their Wiles and Slights they have caught Thouſands of unſtable Souls, but thro' much Labour and Pains by my ſelf and others, there has been ſuch a Diſcovery made of their Books, and the Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies and Corrupt Doctrine contained in them, that now their very Ringleaders themſelves have refuſed either to own or diſown them, or the Doctrines contained in them; by which many of their Hearers begin to queſtion the Pretenſions of their Leaders, and many are come off from them, and have been Baptized into the Chriſtian Faith, by the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> and now they have ſtarted a new Gain, and uſed another Slight, and cunning Piece of Craft, whereby they watch all Opportunities to deceive the People; namely, to put forth a printed Sheet, under the Diſguiſe of a Member of the
<pb facs="tcp:103405:3"/>Church of <hi>England,</hi> with a Deſign to abuſe her, and to deceive others, as the following Diſcourſe will ſhew; and whereby we may ſee they grow worſe and worſe; and this the Apoſtle fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw: And therefore, like careful Watchmen, gave us warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, as in the Places above-cited. To which, let me add St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Prophetical Care, Admonition and Caution, <hi>2 Pet. 2.1, 2. But there were alſo falſe Prophets among the People, even as there</hi> ſhall <hi>be falſe Teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable Hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them: And bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtructions; and many ſhall follow their Pernitious Ways; by reaſon of whom, the way of Truth ſhall be evil ſpoken of.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now how far theſe and other of the like Truths, (left upon Record by the Primitive Inſpired Paſtors and Teachers of the Doctrine of Salvation) are verified in our Days, may be ſeen, and ought to be more laid to Heart by us, than I fear we do: For it hath been manifeſt, and clearly proved, that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> above all others, that I am ſenſible of, are the very Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that deny the Lord that bought them, and ſhed his moſt precious Blood for them; were they but willing to accept of ſo great Salvation on Goſpel Terms. For ſays <hi>W. Penn</hi> in his <hi>Serious Apology,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 146. That the Outward Perſon that ſuffer'd (at</hi> Jeruſalem) <hi>was properly the Son of God, we utterly deny,</hi> &amp;c. Here then we ſee the Holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Words fulfilled; for he or they that deny him that ſuffered at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> upon the Tree of the Croſs, to be the Son of God, I do affirm he or they, whoever they be, deny the Lord that bought them, and will bring upon themſelves ſwift Deſtruction; yea, and as many as ſuck in the Poyſon of their Doctrine, unleſs they repent thereof. But <hi>W. Penn</hi> avouches the ſame in his <hi>Chriſtian Quaker, and his Divine Teſt.</hi> &amp;c. p. <hi>97, 98.</hi> and in many other Places. See alſo <hi>Iſ. Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>'s Book, <hi>A Queſtion to Profeſſors,</hi> &amp;c. p. <hi>33.</hi> Now the Scriptures diſtinguiſh between Chriſt and the Garment he wore; between him that came, and the Body in which he came; between the Subſtance that was vailed, and the Vail that vailed it. There was plainly <hi>He,</hi> and the Body <hi>in which</hi> He <hi>came. There was the</hi> Outward Veſſel, <hi>and the</hi> Inward Life. <hi>This we certainly know, and</hi> can never call the Bodily Garment Chriſt, <hi>but that which</hi> appeared, <hi>and</hi> dwelt in the Body.</p>
            <p>Again, ſee <hi>W. Bayly</hi>'s <hi>Work, p. 300, 307.</hi> quoted at large in my Book, <hi>The Quakers ſet in their true Light,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 43.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:103405:3"/>Whereas <hi>W. Penn</hi> denies the Perſon that ſuffer'd at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> to be the Son of God, as above-quoted, and <hi>Iſ. Penning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> tells you, they can never call him Chriſt, only ſomething that was within him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this <hi>W. Bayly</hi> he makes the ſame Diſtinction, and therefore to ſhew, that theſe Quaker-Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers deny the Lord that bought them, and bring in damnable Hereſies, I ſhall in Two or Three Inſtances ſhew, <hi>Mat. 16.13. Whom do Men ſay that I the Son of Man am?</hi> v. <hi>16. Thou art Chriſt, the Son of the Living God.</hi> V. <hi>17. Bleſſed art thou,</hi> Simon Bar-jona; <hi>for Fleſh and Blood hath not reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it unto thee, but my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> Read alſo <hi>Acts 5.30, 31. The God of our Fathers raiſed up Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, whom ye ſlew and hang'd on a Tree; him hath God exalted with his Right Hand to be a Prince, and a Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, for to give Repentance to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Forgiveneſs of Sins.</hi> Cap. <hi>2.</hi> V. <hi>36. Therefore let all the Houſe of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael <hi>know aſſuredly, that God hath made</hi> that ſame <hi>Jeſus whom ye ſlew and hang'd on a Tree, both Lord and Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I would ask the <hi>Quakers</hi> whether their Light within, which they call Chriſt, was ever hang'd on a Tree, run thro' with a Spear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus much then to ſhew, that the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> are the very Men that deny the Lord that bought them, and that have brought in Damnable Hereſies; who by their Slights and cunning Craftineſs, lye in wait to deceive; and the way to keep their People blind, is to prepoſſeſs them againſt the Scriptures, (which I think they have more than ſufficiently done, by calling them Death, Duſt, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware, and the like Contemptuous Names:) For ſhould they read St. <hi>Luke 2.</hi> and the Evangeliſts thorowly, and the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Holy Apoſtles, and their Epiſtles, they would ſoon find that the Perſon that ſuffered on the Tree of the Croſs at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> was the Son of God, and the Saviour of the World, in Oppoſition to the Doctrine of all <hi>Jews, Mahometans, Deiſts,</hi> and <hi>Quakers.</hi> And thus I conclude this Head, referring the Reader to my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs,</hi> &amp;c. p. <hi>150,</hi> to <hi>174.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Finally, I heartily recommend to the well-diſpoſed amongſt the Hearers of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> the frequent reading of the Holy Scriptures, and other good Books, for their Information and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: For as Ignorance cannot be the Mother of Chriſtian Devotion, neither will it be any Excuſe in the great Day of Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, eſpecially when we conſider the Means of Knowledge is ſo plentiful in this our Chriſtian Nation. Wherefore read <hi>2 Theſ. 1.8.</hi> How that God will take Vengeance on them that know
<pb facs="tcp:103405:4"/>him not, at well as on them that obey not the Goſpel of out Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; and the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah 27.11.</hi> complained, ſaying, <hi>It is a People of no Underſtanding; therefore he that made them will have no Mercy on them, and he that formed them will ſhew them no Favour,</hi> &amp;c. How then ſhould this encourage you to read ſome other Books, beſides thoſe of your Friends? What if your Teachers frown on you? And what if they ſet your Fathers and Mothers, your Wives and Children againſt you? Firſt, Do your Duty to God, and next to your ſeveral Relations: But you that are Maſters of Families, God expects more of you than of others; He hath made Man chief Ruler in his Family, and put all in Subjection to him. <hi>Sarah</hi> was a good Woman, ſhe obeyed her Husband, and call'd him Lord: And <hi>Num. 30.</hi> his Sovereign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty over his Family is Confirmed and Ratified by the Apoſtles; but your Teachers have ſet your Wives at Liberty from this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo that I know whenever you turn your Faces to <hi>Sionward,</hi> and begin to embrace the Articles of the Chriſtian Faith; to read Books wrote againſt the <hi>Quakers,</hi> to conſider, and ſee whether it is ſo, as is reported: I ſay, when any of you come thus to examine, and ſee for your ſelves, you will have hard Work; but then, you that have good Wives, they will be as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, <hi>Prov. 12.4. As a Crown to your Heads:</hi> Yea, as both Shield and Buckler againſt all your Enemies: But if otherwiſe, ſhe'll be as Rottenneſs to your Bones, which cauſeth a Stink and Noiſom Smell: She'll not only watch for your Halting, but be glad to diſcover all your Humane Frailties, or any Perſonal Fault ſhe can find, and all to gratifie your Leaders, who then will turn your Implaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Enemies: But ſtill keep you ſteddy, and do your part, and God will clear your Innocency; but this let me adviſe too, as one that has gone before you; you muſt caſt down your Crowns, and be willing to be accounted as the Dung of the Earth, and as the Offſcouring of all things; and that where your Mercina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Teachers can prevail, you ſhall not have a Friend left you up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth: But for your Encouragement in this your Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs, the Bible is full of Inſtructions, and many other Books, to which I refer you; and I pray God to diſcover to you the Slights and cunning Craftineſs of your Teachers, whereby they lye in wait to deceive; that ſo you may ſhun their Snare, and eſcape their Net, and fly for your Lives, and come forth of <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon</hi> to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which flows with many good things, which you neither know, nor are yet acquainted with.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:103405:4"/>
            <head>The Chriſtian Miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Vindicated and Diſtinguiſhed from the Antichriſtian Miniſtry of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> according to that Text, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their Fruits.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Have ſeen a Printed Sheet, by a nameleſs Author, ſtiled, <hi>A Letter to the Clergy, &amp;c.</hi> by a [pretended] Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and alſo obſerved how univerſally it is ſpread far and near, in all Towns where-ever I came, and how induſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly it is as well diſperſed, as eſpouſed by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and as I am told, read in their Meetings, which is more than ever they did a Chapter in the Bible. Thus do they, like the Revolting <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> worſhip the Works of their own Hands, and dance about this their carved Idol, as they did about the Golden Calf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32. And as when I firſt ſaw it, I took it to be a Project of the <hi>Quakers</hi> forming, ſo I do ſtill; and that not only by the Doctrine therein taught, the Dialect therein uſed, but knowing they can do any thing that may ſerve a turn; Subſcribe Certificates, never handed by the Perſons themſelves, Alter, Add to, and Take from any Matter, whether of the Dead or Living, either in Printing, or Reprinting; for their main Buſineſs and whole Study is, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:103405:5"/>deceive the Nation, and to uſe thoſe Slights, and cunning Craft, which the Apoſtles have given us Warning to be aware of; yea, they can Forge, Lie, Diſſemble, and Act like Knights of the Poſt, under the Diſguiſe of the moſt innocent Saints, and harmleſs Lambs, that ever the Sun did ſhine upon: But alaſs! all that I can ſay, and prove, as in my <hi>Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims Progreſs, &amp;c.</hi> will not ſatisfie them by this laſt Project, I mean their Letter. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, as the Author pretends to be a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and have expoſed the Clergy, therefore, unleſs I <hi>Francis Bugg</hi> can produce one of the Members of the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Society, to teſtifie againſt their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, all is nothing, this is their new Project; and therefore, tho' the <hi>Quakers</hi> are aſhamed to expoſe the Name of their Accuſer, yet I am not; for 'tis <hi>Anne Docwra</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> an ancient and eminent Quaker, a Deaconeſs of the Order of St. <hi>George Fox,</hi> late deceaſed, as in ſome Letters to my ſelf and Mr. <hi>Criſp,</hi> with their ſeveral Dates, and her Broadſide printed, as recited in my <hi>Pilg. Prog. &amp;c.</hi> p. 25, 58. <hi>Jezebel</hi> Withſtood, p. 9, to 12. and other of my Books; all which, I hope, will humor the <hi>Quaker</hi>'s Tool, and great Prop, to uphold their tottering Cauſe, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe ſhe writ thus in her Letter to me, dated the 6th. of <hi>May,</hi> 1683. Viz. <hi>Dear Couſen</hi> Fr. Bugg, <hi>my true Love to thee:—I have given my Witneſs publickly againſt the Lies I found in</hi> Geo. Whitehead<hi>'s Book — We have Knights of the Poſt amongſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:103405:5"/>
            <p n="2">2. Another, 26. Feb. 1682. <hi>Dear Couſen</hi> F. B. G. Whitehead <hi>have ſent me one of his Books for me to read, and there is the old Money Story in it, with I know not what beſides; I was asked by an boneſt Friend, if be</hi> (G. W.) <hi>was not a Jeſuit? I anſwered, nay; it is not ſolid enough for them to own — There is pretty much airy conceited Stuff in it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In her printed Broadſide, <hi>ſtiled, The new projecting Formaliſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I know it is common</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>with ſome of them in their Books of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, to put the Names of ſuch Perſons as they account their Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals, both to Certificates and Books</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Why not then the name of a Member of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>in the room of a real</hi> Quaker.</note>, <hi>ſometimes without the Conſent of the Parties, whoſe Names are Inſerted, and ſometimes with Conſent, thro ſlaviſh Fear, of having their Trades Obſtructed and Ruined by Publick Defamations. Two Years ago I ſaw a ſmall Book, worded by an able Penman,</hi> (G. W.) <hi>wherein was my Name, as a Witneſs, without my Conſent, to Teſtifie more than was true, which I muſt diſown: — Yea, a barefac'd Lie, and an undeniable Truth, ſo cloſely Interwoven, that it is not eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered—Their ſeparate Men's Meetings have been the Nurſeries of Contention, and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, the chief Cauſe of this long-grinding Perſecution;</hi> (for this ſhe wrote about 1683.) <hi>the Magiſtrates has upbraided me as one that adhered to them, looking upon thoſe Meetings, as
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:103405:6"/>more dangerous to the Peace of the Nation</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">This Time will beſt demonſtrate, if theſe Meetings and their Fund be not taken into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</note>, <hi>than our Publick Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings;</hi> (with Doors open) <hi>ſeparate Meeting have ſerved to little Purpoſe, but to ſhelter great Bellies, obſtruct Lawful Marriages, and to ingroſs honeſt Friend's Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties to themſelves; — the moſt innocent ſelf-denying People have been the Subject of their Clamorous Tongue, when the Looſe and Vicious, the Covetous, Proud, Lying Hypocrities, have been covered and protected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. In a Letter to Mr. <hi>Criſp</hi> from <hi>Anne Docwra, Sept.</hi> 20. 1683. Sam. Cater<hi>'s Narrative is come out in Print—I ſuſpect</hi> G. Whitehead <hi>to be the Author of it;</hi> Sam. <hi>is not Sophiſter great enough, to twiſt his Matter together ſo cunningly, either to make Truth go for a Lie, or a Lie go for Truth: It is part of a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter I wrote to</hi> Sam. Cater, <hi>concerning my Couſen</hi> F. Bugg, <hi>wherein they have added a few Words, that quite alters the Senſe of my Letter; neither have they put in the greateſt part of it, which would have overthrown their whole Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Again, That dated <hi>Feb.</hi> 13. 1683. <hi>viz.</hi> Sam. Cater <hi>(ſays</hi> Anne) <hi>is very angry, becauſe I call him to an Account for bringing me in for a Witneſs in his Narrative; moſt of that he has written concerning me is falſe, but not all of it; he hath mixed a Lie and Truth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103405:6"/>
            <p n="6">6. In another Letter to Mr. <hi>Criſp, Mar.</hi> 25. 1684. ſhe thus expreſt her ſelf; Sam. Cater <hi>has been lately with me, clamouring againſt</hi> F. Bugg <hi>and</hi> John Ainſloe; <hi>I have had a ſharp Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him about his Narrative, wherein he has uſed my Name in Print, to juſtifie him in his Contentious Pamphlet with</hi> F.B. <hi>about Money—I laid it before him ſmartly, before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Friends; he is very bold, and the moſt</hi> confident Liar <hi>that ever I met with; I laid the Record againſt</hi> John Ainſloe <hi>before him— alſo</hi> G. Whitehead<hi>'s falſe Certificate about the (ſaid) Record, in his</hi> Judgment fixed, <hi>that it is an abuſeful Forgery; for ſome of thoſe, whoſe Names are to the Certificate, abſolutely diſowns it, and ſay they ſet their Hands to none. It is very ſad</hi> (ſaid ſhe) <hi>that Men ſhould be ſo confident in their Wickedneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, by the Author of this Scurrilous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, under Conſideration, he argues, in <hi>p.</hi> 5. that it was not the Diſciples of Chriſt, and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that call'd our Lord a Wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Bibber, a Friend to Publicans and Sinners, a Babbler, but his profeſs'd Enemies, the <hi>Scribes, Phariſees,</hi> and Unbelievers; and thereupon he drew his Concluſion, that the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are not Chriſt's Miniſters, and think this will affect their ſacred Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being thus charged by a Member of their own Church; then by the ſame Rule of argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, this Woman was, and ſtill is of their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion; a Writer in Defence of them, and in their Unity: Therefore, I ſay, it muſt affect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103405:7"/>them; and that ſhe then ſpake the Truth, my ſelf and many others are Witneſſes of moſt of theſe things, or things equivolent; and were I to enlarge upon the Teſtimonies of <hi>John Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinſon, John Story,</hi> and many other <hi>Quakers,</hi> who liv'd and dy'd <hi>Quakers,</hi> I could greatly enlarge hereupon: But I thought I had done, when I ſhew'd in <hi>Jezebel Withſtood</hi> how this Woman wheels about; and to creep into their Unity, is become Scandalous, in her now wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and with the Dog turns and licks up her old Vomit, which ſhe ſpued forth many Years ſince, and when a <hi>Quaker</hi> too: But what is her Teſtimony, but this, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> Teachers are the moſt confident Liars, abuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Forgers, Jeſuits, and Knights of the Poſt; that their Monthly, Quarterly, and Yearly Meetings, are Nurſeries of Contention, who wickedly forge Certificates, and put the Names of their Vaſſals, and tame Slaves, to Books, without their Licence; or elſe, if they ſubmit not to their Tyranny and Uſurpation, they may expect to be ruined in their Trades and Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which is moſt true; and that the moſt Innocent among them are the Subject of their Clamorous Tongue, whilſt the Vicious, Proud, Covetous, Inſulting Liars, are protected and encouraged; and if ſo, as ſo it is, and hath been, no marvel that the <hi>Quakers</hi> put out ſuch a Letter to the Clergy, under the Mask and Vizor of a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and then ſend it up and down the Nation, to deceive the unwary Readers.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:103405:7"/>
            <p>Beſides, the very Title of this Pamphlet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers the Juggle, <hi>viz. A Letter to the Clergy, &amp;c.</hi> wherein they are deſired to challenge the Quakers <hi>once more;</hi> now <hi>once more</hi> implies, the Clergy had already, or firſt challenged the <hi>Quakers,</hi> when indeed the <hi>Quakers</hi> evaded my Challenge, and turned the Challenge upon the Clergy; yea, to any of their Cloth, as is plain from <hi>p.</hi> 50. and other Parts of the <hi>Quakers</hi> own Book, <hi>A Defence of the People call'd Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> &amp;c. Printed 1699. all which I have made appear in my Book, <hi>Quakeriſm expoſed to Publick Cenſure,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But this their Falacy <hi>once more</hi> looks like the Forehead of <hi>John Feild,</hi> who I take to be the Author of a Letter ſent me to <hi>Milden-Hall,</hi> at the ſame time that both <hi>Feild</hi> and I ſaw one another at the <hi>Commons Lobby</hi> every Day; namely, <hi>March</hi> the 31th. 1699. directed not to <hi>Fr Bugg</hi> the elder, but to <hi>Fr. Bugg,</hi> of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den-Hall,</hi> that ſo it might come into my Son's Hand, and ſerve to ſet him againſt me; for Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit-like, their Work has been, not only to ſet the Clergy and all Mankind againſt me, but my Wife and Children: But I thank God my Son ſees thro' many of their Jeſuitical and Sly Inſinuations; a few of his Words are as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth:</p>
            <p>F. Bugg, <hi>Any reaſonable Man might think, that after thou hadſt writ ſo many Books, to ſo little Purpoſe, thou ſhouldſt forbear to write any more; for what Effect hath all thy Books had?—Except it be amongſt thoſe that are as
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:103405:8"/>bad as thy ſelf, who do highly exalt and eſteem them, and that for no other Reaſon, but that they are againſt thoſe that have diſcovered and brought to light many of their Cheats, and evil Practices, which long lay hid in the Dark, whereby the Simple was deceived,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And that this <hi>J. Feild</hi> does manifeſtly reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Author of the ſaid <hi>Letter to the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> he, like him, if he be not the very Perſon, ſubſcribed his ſaid Letter, <hi>i.e. Thus I ſubſcribe my ſelf,—refuſing to write my Name at length, J. F—d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much then, <hi>Firſt,</hi> to ſhew, That the Author of the ſaid <hi>Letter to the Clergy</hi> may be a real <hi>Quaker,</hi> and probably <hi>J. Feild</hi> is the Man, becauſe it bears his Image: <hi>Firſt,</hi> In his Impudence, <hi>Once more: Secondly,</hi> From his Practice, in not writing his Name at length: <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in his Hypocriſie, to write to me at <hi>Milden-Hall,</hi> when he ſaw me every Day in <hi>London: Fourthly,</hi> From his Malicious End and Deſign therein, to ſow Diſcord between me, and my Wife, and Children; all which are the real Fruits of a real <hi>Quaker,</hi> and not of a Member of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> And therefore, when I conſider'd of the Evil which might enſue the ſpreading of this <hi>Letter to the Clergy,</hi> I ſpoke of it to ſeveral worthy and able Men, who thought it not worth the noticing; and then, tho' I once thought I had ſaid enough to it in <hi>Quakeriſm expoſed,</hi> &amp;c. p. 12. yet I could not well paſs it, but ſhew the World, by what Falacies Quakeriſm is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:103405:8"/>ſupported; and now I ſhall proceed to ſhew, that the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are Chriſt's Miniſters, and that the Quaker-Teachers are Deceivers, and Antichriſtian Deluders, and that too by this pretended Member of the Church of <hi>England</hi> s own Method.</p>
            <p>For having by this time ſhewed ſufficient Grounds to believe, that the <hi>Quakers,</hi> who can thus forge, who thus can ſet their Vaſſals Names to Books and Certificates, and are the moſt confident Liars, even Knights of the Poſt, as aſſerted by one, and no ſmall one neither, of their own Society, I hope it will not ſeem improbable, but that a <hi>Quaker</hi> may be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this <hi>Letter to the Clergy,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding I have proved in <hi>Jezebel Withſtood,</hi> that ſhe is as great a Liar, Forger, and Knight of the Poſt, as any of the <hi>Quakers:</hi> For therein ſhe is a right <hi>Quaker,</hi> and in her Element as brisk as a Fiſh in the Water; and therefore, as I ſaid, I ſhall now proceed to prove the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Chriſt's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and that by his own Method too, that ſo I may the better wound him with his own Weapon; and therefore, tho' he walk diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I ſhall draw my Bow at a Venture, not doubting but to ſhoot between the Joints and the Harneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tree</hi> (ſays he, p. 4.) <hi>is known by its Fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I read <hi>Matth.</hi> the 7th. that Chriſt himſelf gave us warning of falſe Prophets and Decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:103405:9"/>which ſhould ariſe, but by their Fruits, ſaid he, ye ſhall know them; <hi>v.</hi> 15. <hi>Beware of falſe Prophets,</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>which ſhall come to you in Sheeps clothing, but inwardly they are Ravening Wolves:</hi> V. 16. <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their Fruits: Do Men gather Grapes of Thorns, or Figs of Thiſtles?</hi> Now what is this, but to tell us, that in the laſt Times there ſhall ariſe, as in <hi>Matth.</hi> 24.24. <hi>Falſe Chriſts and falſe Prophets, and ſhall ſhew great Signs and Wonders; inſomuch, that if it were poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, they ſhall deceive the very Elect.</hi> Such ſhall be their counterfeit Meekneſs, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and outward Sanctity, as if they were the very Saints of the moſt High, when in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they are the verieſt Hypocrites, Liars, Forgers, and wicked Impoſters, that ever the World knew, as this <hi>Anne Docwra</hi> (not an Unbeliever of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Doctrine, but one of their own Writers and Defenders of their Faith) hath ſhewed very plainly: And thus far, <hi>By their Fruit you may know them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come next to this Author's Method touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Doctrine; for ſince I have underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken him, I am willing to follow him into all his ſculking Corners, and to trace him in his Bye-Paths, and ſhall at laſt challenge him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the open Field; and who knows, but I may bring him out at laſt; if not, I hope I ſhall diſcover his Night Walks, and Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: But to his Method of Trial, ſee <hi>p.</hi> 3. where he cites Chriſt's Commiſſion to St. <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 26. namely, <hi>To open the blind Eyes,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103405:9"/>to unſtop the deaf Ears, to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, and from Satan's Power to God.</hi> But, <hi>Reader,</hi> he has left out great part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Commiſſion, and therefore to his own Confutation let him look <hi>p. Ibid.</hi>—where he grants, <hi>That glad Tydings of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is part of the Goſpel, but there goeth ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other Rights with it; which leave out any one of them, and it is no more the Goſpel, than the Trinity is the Trinity, leaving out one of the Three Perſons:</hi> Inſomuch, that by his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the Commiſſion of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> above ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.18. he, Quaker-like, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the more like himſelf, has left out great part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Commiſſion, as knowing it not agreeable to the <hi>Quakers</hi> Doctrine, Faith, or Principles; and therefore, to ſhew this ſculking obſcure Enemy to the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, his Inconſiſtency with himſelf, I ſhall cite the whole Verſe, <hi>viz. To open their Eyes, and to turn them from Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan unto God: That they may receive Forgiveneſs of Sins, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them that are ſanctified, thro Faith that is in me.</hi> Now theſe Words, that they may receive Forgiveneſs of Sins, and Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them which are ſanctified <hi>thro' Faith that is in me,</hi> he leaves out, as a Sign it is not within the <hi>Quakers</hi> Creed, as anon I ſhall ſhew; and indeed, all the time I was a <hi>Quaker,</hi> I do not remember that ever I heard this whole Verſe quoted, only the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer part, as recited by this diſguiſed Author,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103405:10"/>to prove their Light within was Chriſt; yea, the whole and compleat Chriſt, as <hi>Burroughs,</hi> their great Prophet, teaches in his Works, <hi>p.</hi> 149. I will mention here but one Scripture more, which the <hi>Quakers</hi> pervert, and which I never underſtood, until I came to learn it of ſuch, as this Sculking Adverſary would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame; namely, the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> It is <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6, 7, 8. So far they frequently quoted, to prove their Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was the compleat Chriſt, and Righteouſneſs of Faith; leaving always out, ſo far as ever I remember, the 9th. Verſe, <hi>viz. That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy Mouth the Lord Jeſus: And ſhalt believe in thine Heart, that God hath raiſed him from the Dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> No, this Faith and Confeſſion of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and his Reſurrection from the Dead, is out of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Creed: And therefore, like this Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to Chriſtianity, when he cites St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Commiſſion, and leaves out that part, <hi>Thro' Faith that is in me,</hi> ſo do the <hi>Quaker</hi>-Teachers leave out, <hi>That if thou ſhalt confeſs with thy Mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine Heart, that God hath raiſed him from the Dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> And thus, like Twins, begot by one Father, and brought forth by one Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the falſe Church or Synagogue of Satan, do this ſculking Adverſary agree in the Unity of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Doctrine, which ſtill confirms me that he is a <hi>Quaker</hi> in Diſguiſe: But to proceed, to diſcover by the Doctrine taught
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103405:10"/>by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Doctrine taught by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> which of the Twain are Chriſt's Miniſters; this is the Method he has propoſed, and it is the Method I ſhall take.</p>
            <p>But firſt let me obſerve to the <hi>Reader</hi> one Paſſage, wherein the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and this Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Obſcure Fellow, which they keep behind the Curtain, agree like Birds of another Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>viz.</hi> Page the 7th. of this <hi>Letter, &amp;c.</hi> and another of their Books, wrote by <hi>John Fiddiman,</hi> and others, <hi>p.</hi> 6, to 12. their Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are the ſame, and their Words almoſt <hi>Verbatim.</hi> The latter I have anſwered in <hi>Quakeriſm expoſed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 46. which Anſwer may ſerve for this alſo; but that I may ſhew the Nature of theſe Beaſts or Birds of Prey, give me leave to ſhew their Complexion, that the World may judge whether they be not Twins, begot by one Father, <hi>i. e.</hi> The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father of all Liars, and falſe Accuſers, and brought forth by one Mother, Myſtery <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> the Mother of Harlots. The Words are theſe, <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>You charge the</hi> Quakers <hi>with Blaſphemy, and is not that very Charge blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, in ſaying, The Light within, as taught by them, leads them into theſe, and many more Errors? Is Chriſt the Author of Blaſphemy? You have now charged it upon him</hi> (Chriſt) <hi>with a Witneſs—Who ſaid, I am the Light of the World—So that, Sirs, you have not only charged the</hi> Quakers, <hi>but Chriſt too, as high as you charge them,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:103405:11"/>
            <p>This then is the Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that the <hi>Quakers</hi> ſo much boaſt of, and glory in, even by all Signs and Tokens, <hi>John Feild:</hi> For if they can do as their Siſter <hi>Anne Docwra</hi> ſays they can, that is, Lie Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble, Forge, and Act in the very ſame Strain, like Knights of the Poſt: Then are they fitly qualified to write any thing, and to bear any Name, whether Church of <hi>England-man,</hi> or <hi>Quaker,</hi> that ſuits beſt with their Intereſt; for they ſtick at nothing; and therefore I take the true Reaſon, why this Pamphlet is put out by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> under the Name of a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be this; of late their own Books are (even by many of their own People) ſo loathed, becauſe of the Lies and Forgeries, Errors and Blaſphemies contained in them: That even the Teachers themſelves are aſhamed or afraid, or both, to own and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them: Therefore they put this Varniſh upon their Works of Darkneſs, as thoſe falſe Coiners do; who, to cover their Braſs, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther baſe Metal, cover and gloſs it over with Silver, and then, for the preſent, it will paſs with many; but this was ſoon ſeen, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, and accounted to be not worth the noticing; But alas, ſuch is the Stupidity of the ignorant Followers of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and the cunning Craftineſs of their Ringleaders, that it does great Hurt amongſt them; and for their ſakes, theſe Wiles of Satan ought to be laid o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen. But I commend Father <hi>Penn;</hi> he had more Wit in his Anger, than to recite the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy's
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103405:11"/>Fifth Charge, as by them ſtated; he is not ſuch a Fool; but do know, that the Light within, AS taught by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> leaves them without any certain Rule, and expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them to thoſe Errors and Blaſphemies the Clergy char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them with, and many other Errors. And therefore, when he had Occaſion, in their new ſham <hi>Briſtol</hi>-Creed, to recite it, he politickly left out the Word AS, and ſaid, <hi>The Light within us, taught by us,</hi> ſeeming thereby to know ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, that the Light within, AS taught by them, did expoſe them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I having firſt replied to <hi>John Fiddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, &amp;c.</hi> who by the Sameneſs of the Arguments, ſeems to be the Author of this <hi>Letter;</hi> but I rather take it to be <hi>John Feild,</hi> for the Reaſons given. And next, not only the Clergy, but my ſelf have fully proved this Fifth Charge, <hi>viz. That the Light within, AS taught by the</hi> Quakers, <hi>leaves them without any certain Rule, and expoſes them to the recited Blaſphemies by the Clergy;</hi> which was,</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Blaſphemy againſt God.</item>
               <item>II. Blaſphemy againſt Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>III. Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Scriptures.</item>
            </list>
            <p>I ſay, theſe things being firſt proved by the Clergy in their Book, <hi>A Brief Diſcovery, &amp;c.</hi> and by me, by way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional Proof, becauſe one Book may come where another does not; and not only ſo, but from many Inſtances out of the Scriptures I have from thence ſhewed; that the Way, Manner and Method of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Teaching, is directly contrary to the Way, Manner and Method of the Prophets, Chriſt, and the Apoſtles, and all Chriſtian Churches to this Day; but that I may, ſo far as I can ſafely purſue the Method directed to, by this obſcure Author, I ſhall now proceed to diſtinguiſh between the Doctrine of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Doctrine of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> out of their Books, and ſo vindicate the one, and reject the other.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Tree is known</hi> (ſays he) <hi>by its Fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Clergy's Doctrine.</head>
               <p>They preach Faith in the Crucified Jeſus, who was Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and with St. <hi>Peter</hi> they agree, who ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.16. in Anſwer to the Queſtion, which Chriſt put to his Diſciples, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>Whom do Men ſay that I the Son of Man am? Thou art</hi> (ſaid <hi>Peter) Chriſt, the Son of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God.</hi> They agree alſo with St. <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 5.30, 31. <hi>The
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103405:12"/>God of our Fathers raiſed up Jeſus, whom ye ſlew and hanged on a Tree: Him has God exalted with his Right Hand, to be a Prince, and a Saviour, for to give Repentance to</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and Forgiveneſs of Sins.</hi> They preach and believe according to St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, <hi>John</hi> 5.22. <hi>For the Father judgeth no Man, but hath committed all Judgment unto the Son.</hi> V. 27. <hi>And have given him Authority to execute Judgment alſo, becauſe he is the Son of Man.</hi> And they Believe and Teach all other neceſſary Truths out of the Holy Scriptures, and have many Witneſſes, that their Doctrine tend (to all who receive the Truth in the Love of it) to open their Hearts, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by turned from Darkneſs, to the Light of the Glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and from <hi>Sathan</hi>'s Power, Reign and Government, to the Power, Providence and Protection of God Almighty, in order to receive Forgiveneſs of Sins, thro' a Sincere and Hearty Repentance, and an Humble Confeſſion; and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pardon of the ſame, for the ſake of Chriſt, our alone Mediator and Advocate, and thro' Faith in his Name. All this they Preach and Teach, according to the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; tho' I grant, that where it is not mixed with Faith in the Hearers, there is no profiting to ſuch; nor were they profited by the Sermons of Chriſt, or his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, who did not believe, tho' they might receive the Lord's Supper, as <hi>Judas</hi> did, and be Baptized, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> was: So that the Miniſtry is not to be blamed, in that ſuch as reſiſt the Truth, and rebel againſt it, are not profited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Quakers Doctrine.</head>
               <p>They Teach, that the Perſon that ſuffer'd at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was not properly the Son of God: That he was only a Vail, a Garment, a Veſſel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which they can never call Chriſt: That the Name [Chriſt] belongs to every believing <hi>Quaker,</hi> as well as to the Head: That all Power in Heaven and Earth is committed to the Light [Within]; and for this, they quote <hi>John</hi> 5.22. They Teach, that the Son of Man was before the Incarnation: That they cannot pray for the Prieſts, but for their Deſtruction: That the Miniſters that Preach Chriſt without, and bid People believe in him, as he is in Heaven above, are falſe Miniſters: They teach likewiſe, that the Light in them is Chriſt, and that this Chriſt doth offer up himſelf in them, a Sacrifice to God, by which the Wrath and Juſtice of God is appeaſed:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103405:12"/>They teach, that the very Chriſt of God is <hi>Within</hi> them, and that in them he doth Intercede for them, They teach, that upon, and for theſe Reaſons, there is not that need of Publiſhing or Preaching the Literal Knowledge of Chriſt; for ſay they, the Hiſtorical Knowledge of Chriſt is believed by all ſorts, pretending to Chriſtianity; His Death, His Miracles, His Riſing, His Aſcending into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. See <hi>Quakeriſm Expoſed, &amp;c. p.</hi> 55. <hi>Sheet to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> 1693. and my other Books, ſet forth theſe Proofs out of the <hi>Quakers</hi> moſt noted Authors, only I here ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract; for it is to ſhew the Tendency of their Doctrine, and wherein it differs from the Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Clergy's Doctrine.</head>
               <p>They teach according to St. <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 2.10. That God hath highly exalted Chriſt, and given him a Name above every Name: They teach, that His Sufferings were Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and that the Sufferings of the Martyrs was the Seed of the Church: They teach, that the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are the Word of God, and Rule of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice to Mankind, and of greater Authority than any other Book: They Preach out of it to the People, according to the uſual Cuſtom of the Church, both Jewiſh and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, having the Example of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 4. <hi>And as his Cuſtom was, he went into the Synagogue on the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath-Day, and ſtood up for to read, and there was delivered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the Book of the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah; <hi>and when he opened the Book, he found the place where it was written,</hi> &amp;c. See al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 34.18, 19, 35. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 8.1, 2. <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.10, 11. They Teach and Practice the Commands of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations Baptizing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.19, 20. <hi>Do this in Remembrance of me.</hi> When they pray, they ſay after this manner, according to Chriſt's Precept and Command, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Forgive us,</hi> &amp;c. They Teach Subjection to Magiſtrates, according to <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.21. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13, 14, 17. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. Wives to their Husbands, according to <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.22. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.18. <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Numb.</hi> 30. And all other Chriſtian Duties; and this I take to be a Proof of their Miniſtry.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Quakers Doctrine.</head>
               <p>They teach, that the Name Chriſt belongs to every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, as well as to the Head; utterly denying the Perſon
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103405:13"/>that ſuffered to be the Son of God: They teach, that the Sufferings of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in this Age are <hi>Greater,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> Unjuſt, than in the Days of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and Martyrs, or any time ſince: They teach, that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are not the Word of God, nor Rule of Faith and Practice; and that it is Conjuration to Preach out of them; and that they are Death, Duſt, Serpents Meat, Beaſtly Ware. They queſtion whether <hi>Moſes</hi> or <hi>Hermes</hi> was the firſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of them; and teach, that what good Men ſpake was ill expreſſed, what wiſe Men ſpake was ill applied, and that what the true Prophets ſpake was falſe, and what the falſe Prophets ſpake was true, at leaſt ſome of all theſe four Inſtances, which tend to overthrow the Divine Authority of the Scriptures. See their Book, <hi>The Quakers Refuge fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 17. They alſo teach, that what they Speak [or Write] from the Spirit of Truth, is of greater Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity than the Bible: They teach, that no Command in Scripture is any further obliging to them, than they are convinced by their Light Within of their Duty of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; and thereupon throw off Baptiſm, the Lord's Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; affirming (in <hi>Penn</hi>'s <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 108, 109.) that Circumciſion is as much in force as Water Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſm, and the Paſchal Lamb as Bread and Wine: — I do Renounce (ſays he, and in him all the <hi>Quakers</hi>) and can te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie from the ſame Spirit, by which <hi>Paul</hi> renounced Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, that they are rejected, as not now required, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and accordingly they have rejected univerſally theſe two Ordinances. Inſtituted by Chriſt himſelf this 49 Years. They teach by their Practice and Example, that it is not neceſſary to make Confeſſion of Sins to God, nor to ask Pardon for Chriſt's ſake; nor can they produce one Proof out of their Books that ſo teach: They teach, that their Light within is the Magiſtrate, the Husband, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and that no Obedience is due to either, when the Commands of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Magiſtrate or Husband contradict their Light Within. To which they add, that all Power in Heaven and Earth is committed to their Light, and that every Soul ought to be ſubject to it, as to the higher Power; quoting <hi>John</hi> 5.22. See <hi>Coale</hi>'s Works, <hi>p.</hi> 93. and <hi>Smith</hi>'s <hi>Primer,</hi> p. 13. And upon this Suppoſition they leave out of their Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age Certificates the Wifes Promiſe of Obedience to her Husband; inſomuch, that I have heard ſome of the Women
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103405:13"/>
                  <hi>Quakers</hi> ſay, that they ſaw no Reaſon, either to Submit to, or Reverence their Husbands.</p>
               <p>I might proceed to a Thouſand Things more of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to ſhew the Diſparity of the Doctrine of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and the Doctrine of the <hi>Quakers;</hi> but this may ſhew which are Chriſt's Miniſters, and which are Antichriſtian Seducers: And they are not changed; they tell you ſo, only ſee Cauſe to word the Matter otherwiſe, whilſt they intend the ſame thing: As <hi>Whitehead,</hi> that Forger, ſays in Print, and by the honeſteſt of the <hi>Quakers</hi> have been thought to be a Jeſuit; only his Writings are not ſolid enough.</p>
               <p>Now if this obſcure Author thinks I miſrepreſent the Doctrine of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> let him pull off his Mask, and come forth, and meet me, and I will prove what I ſay, from the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books, upon timely notice: For tho' Dr. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dredge,</hi> Dean of <hi>Chriſt's-Church-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> has bought my Quaker-Books, and given them to the Colledge-Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to remain as Monuments of the <hi>Quakers</hi> Errors, and Blaſphemous Principles, yet I can have them at a Months Notice: For there they are ſet in order; firſt, <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> next <hi>Muggleton</hi> and <hi>Reeve</hi>'s Works, which contain more than a Thouſand Pages in Quarto; next <hi>Fox</hi>'s <hi>Great Myſtery;</hi> then <hi>Burrough</hi>'s, <hi>Fiſher</hi>'s, <hi>Smith</hi>'s, <hi>Hubberthorn</hi>'s, <hi>Bayly</hi>'s, <hi>Coale</hi>'s, and other Folio's, beſides many of the Books of <hi>Penn</hi>'s, <hi>Whitehead</hi>'s, and others of the <hi>Quakers</hi> moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Writers, about 300 in number: As <hi>Nayler</hi>'s, <hi>Lawſon</hi>'s, <hi>Atkinſon</hi>'s, <hi>Howgill</hi>'s, <hi>Pennington</hi>'s, and others; and I am ſtill getting more to add to them: And let this ſerve for an Advertiſement, where a Stock of their Books may be ſeen, together with all I have wrote, bound up together, as a Teſtimony againſt their groſs Errors, and pernicious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
               <p>Again, Whereas this Night-Bird pretends, that Mr. <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> accounts the <hi>Quakers</hi> Orthodox, in that he did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the preſent <hi>Quakers</hi> then there at <hi>Weſt-Dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> upon their Acknowledgment of their Belief of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſound Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, on Condition they would condemn their Blaſphemous Books. This is no more than I and every charitable Man ought to do: But when he ſee they refuſed to perform the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Acknowledgement, the very next <hi>Sunday</hi> in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:103405:14"/>his Pulpit, he did declare, in my Hearing, to all his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, that the <hi>Quakers</hi> Books contained the ancient Hereſies of the <hi>Sabellians, Arians, &amp;c.</hi> and the late Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the <hi>Socinians, Papiſts, &amp;c.</hi> And this ſhews his Sence of Quakeriſm, and that is far enough from approving Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm to be Conſiſtent with Chriſtianity: No; he is an Ancient, Sober and Sound Orthodox Chriſtian, and an Able Miniſter of the Goſpel, and a witneſs againſt Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks and Deceivers, and have often warned his People a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt adhering to their cunning Slights, whereby they lye in wait to deceive.</p>
               <p>But ſays this Corner Scribe, <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>The High-Prieſt had a</hi> Judas <hi>at work for Money, to betray Chriſt into their Hands; have not you a</hi> Judas? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Indeed, if the Name Chriſt belongs to every Believer, as well as to the Head Chriſt, as the <hi>Quakers</hi> teach, then to <hi>Fox, Whitehead, Penn,</hi> as well as to him that ſuffer'd at <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> And upon that foot this Inſinuation might have ſome Colour, and but ſome Colour. For <hi>Firſt,</hi> I did not go to the Prieſts for Money to diſcover them, as <hi>Judas</hi> did, to betray Chriſt, it is well known, that for them, whilſt with them, I ſpent my Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney freely: And when I came to withſtand ſome of their Pernicious Ways, I did not print and expoſe them preſently, but went to them, and in a friendly manner, let them ſee wherein they did not walk uprightly, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Pretenſions, <hi>Firſt,</hi> In exacting Hat-Honour of their Apprentices, Servants, and Inferiors, whilſt they daily refuſed it to their Superiors. <hi>Secondly,</hi> In adviſing their Hearers to be bold, to give up all; and made an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, That they ſhould conſtantly meet (whilſt the Law prohibited their Meetings under great Penalties) and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Forſake, Decline,</hi> nor <hi>Remove</hi> their Meetings, like <hi>Worldly, Fearful,</hi> and <hi>Politick</hi> Profeſſors, meaning the Presbyterians, Independants and Baptiſts, whilſt they themſelves would give up nothing, but to keep themſelves from ſuffering with their Brethren, refuſed to declare their Names and Habitations, whereby they might ſtand in a like ſuffering Capacity with their People, whom they thus exhorted to Boldneſs and Courage, and to give up all; telling them the Fleece would grow again; inſomuch, as that in the Loſs of 13550 <hi>l.</hi> and odd Pounds, the Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers never loſt 50 <hi>l.</hi> as at large ſhewed in my Book, <hi>The
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103405:14"/>Painted Harlot Stript and Whipt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p.</hi> 5, to 40. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I ſhewed them alſo their Hypocriſie, in pleading to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates for Liberty of Conſcience, when they themſelves impoſed on the Conſciences of their Diſciples, the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Women's Meetings, and other Innovations, which <hi>Fox</hi> ſet up, under pretence of a Motion from the Spirit of God, when he took the Headſhip upon him, as at large in my Book, <hi>De Chriſt. Lib.</hi> &amp;c. But did I print and expoſe them, before I privately dealt with them? I tell you nay, thoſe Books will ſhew what Pains I took, by Perſonal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences, by Letters and Propoſitions for an Accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation and Reformation amongſt our ſelves, Two Years together, and more, before I printed; but when all my Endeavours could not prevail, the laſt Means, to ſhew and diſcover their Hypocriſie, was printing, which is and has been the Method of all Reformed Proteſtants, upon their Separation from <hi>Rome</hi>'s Superſtition and Idolatry; and all this many Years, even until 1697. at my own Coſt, until by the <hi>Quakers</hi> proſecuting me, by their Books, by their Indictments in the <hi>Old-Baily, London;</hi> by their Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous Tongues, and Defaming Libels; together with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of them, and others breaking in my Debt, I was reduced, and made uncapable of maintaining my Poſt, and their common Bank was too Powerful for me: But I have Two or Three Queſtions to ask this obſcure Author (and if a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which yet I queſtion) a <hi>Judas. Firſt,</hi> Are all that ſeparate from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and write againſt her, <hi>Judaſes?</hi> If ſo, how many Thouſand <hi>Judaſes</hi> are there among the <hi>Quakers? Secondly,</hi> Are all that receive Money to ſupport them in their Livelihoods, <hi>Judaſes?</hi> Then <hi>G. Whitehead, Fox, Cater,</hi> and all or moſt of the Quaker-Teachers are ſuch. If not, why may not, the Church of <hi>England</hi> be charitable, in their ſupporting their Members, without be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who Crucified the Lord of Life and Glory, as well as the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If this obſcure Author be a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I do not grant, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be a <hi>Quaker</hi> in Diſguiſe, or at leaſt one near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly related to them, peradventure a <hi>Muggletonian,</hi> a <hi>Deiſt,</hi> a <hi>Socinian,</hi> a <hi>Ranter,</hi> or a <hi>Jeſuit.</hi> But ſtill, ſuppoſe he be a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> has he gone to the Clergy? Has he ſpoke privately to them, and endeavour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103405:15"/>a Reformation? And when that would not do, has he gone to their Governors in a Regular way, and that for Two or Three Years together, as I did, before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes them in Print, ſaying, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>Let me go where I will, you are all charged with one thing or other amiſs: Some with Covetouſneſs, ſome with Pride, ſome with Drunkenneſs, indeed what not? For moſt Folks will have one Story or other to tell of a Parſon. Perhaps you'd ſay, that's no new thing; the great Lord Jeſus was call'd a Wine-Bibber, a Friend to Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Sinners; and</hi> Paul <hi>was called a Sinner, and a Babbler. But, Sirs, remember this, thoſe that accuſed Christ and his Apoſtles were not of the ſame Society or Communion with them; they were Unbelievers: But theſe that accuſe you are Men of our own Church,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I ſay, did this <hi>Judas</hi> ever go to any of theſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, whom he thus ſecretly ſmites at? If not, he can be no true Son of the Church, but ſome baſe-born Baſtard Brat, of <hi>Ham</hi>'s Family; and this may be the Reaſon, why he is aſhamed of his Name: But may not I ſay the like of the <hi>Quakers?</hi> (for I am as much a Quaker as he is a true Son of the Church) Do not I here, where ever I come, (or may I not, if I were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly concerned to find out their Immoralities) find ſomething or other amiſs, even amongſt their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Writers, and Defenders of their Faith? Yea, that I do, or may, if I will. How that ſome are Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, ſome are Drunkards (<hi>alias</hi> wet <hi>Quakers,</hi>) ſome are Proud, ſome have been Traytors to their Country, ſome have been hang'd for Felony. See my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs,</hi> &amp;c. But ſays this baſe-born obſcure Scribler, <hi>Sirs, remember, thoſe that called Christ and his Apostles Wine bibbers, Publicans and Sinners, were not of Christ's and the Apostles Commanion, but thoſe that accuſe the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy are of the ſame Communion; and therefore, what</hi> Fran. Bugg <hi>and other Apostates ſay, let it be ever ſo true, let them have Witneſſes to prove what they ſay; let them name the Perſons; let them particularize their Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; tell them when and where; Day, Month, and Year, with all other demonſtrable Arguments; all this is nothing, the</hi> Quakers <hi>are ſtill innocent, ſtill blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, and true Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi> A ſpecial Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> indeed, as Men ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103405:15"/>ſpeaks by the Rule of Contraries: No, nothing avails, unleſs I can produce as good a Member of the Schiſm of Quakeriſm, to teſtifie againſt the Quaker-Teachers, as he is of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who thus expoſes the Clergy, all will not do: But then, to ſuit him, and to bring an equal Parallel, and of which too I can bring many Witneſſes, to ſtrengthen and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roborate her Evidence, it ſhall be <hi>Anne Docwra,</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> eldeſt Daughter of <hi>William Waldgrave</hi> of <hi>Buers,</hi> Son of Sir <hi>William Waldgrave</hi> the younger. I know ſhe loves to have it known that ſhe came of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily above the common Size, as well as this obſcure Author loves to have the Teſtimony of them of the ſame Communion, and I am willing herein to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie them both: And now let us hear what ſhe ſays of the Quaker-Teachers; namely, <hi>That they are the most confident Liars that ever ſhe met with; that they are abuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Forgers, and ſuſpected to be Jeſuits; as like Knights of the Post, as one Pea is like another: That 'tis common with them to ſet the Names of their tame Vaſſals to Books and Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates; and that ſuch as refuſe Submiſſion, to ruin them, both in their Trades and Reputations: That their ſeparate Men's Meetings are Nurſeries of Contention, and dangerous to the Peace of the Nation, and ſerve to little Purpoſe, but to ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter great Bellies, and to ingroſs the Properties of their honest Friends, whilst the Vicious, the Proud, the Covetous, and lying Hypocrites, are covered and protected: It is very ſad</hi> (ſays ſhe) <hi>that Men ſhould be ſo confident in their Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I will appeal to all good Chriſtians, who have read the Hiſtories of the Popiſh Councils, and Club of Cardinals, whether ever there were a more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Tribe of Men. All this I believe is true, and know the greateſt part of it to be ſo; and I know alſo much more of the ſame Nature, and of as deep a Dye, which I have ſet forth in my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs.</hi> But to humor this pretended Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> (whilſt yet I have Grounds to believe him to be a real Quaker) I have produced the Teſtimony of a real Quaker, and one that has been a Quaker nigh 30 Years, and now in the Unity, that ſo it may have the more weight with him, and be a Means to
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103405:16"/>bring him out; to pull off his Mask, and to appear in his own Sanguine Complexion.</p>
               <p>But that we may not want Evidence of what the Quaker-Teachers are, not to mention the many Quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which I could bring out of the Books, wrote againſt the <hi>Quakers</hi> Errors by the Presbyterians, Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants and Baptiſts, (who, agreeable to the Church of <hi>England</hi> hold the Fundamentals of Chriſtianity; however, differing in ſome Ceremonies relating to Diſcipline, Order and Government) which would be too voluminous here to recite; yet having their Judgment of the Fruits and Doctrines of Quakeriſm, well atteſted, I ſhall here incert it, that ſo the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of Chriſtianity, whether the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or the Proteſtant Diſſenters, who agree in the main, may ſtand by themſelves on the one Hand, ſtudying the things that make for Peace, and the Increaſe of Love and mutual Forbearance one with another; all ſtriving together for the Maintenance of the common Cauſe of Chriſtianity; and the <hi>Quakers, Ranters, Muggletonians,</hi> and their Brethren, the <hi>Deists, Socinians,</hi> and <hi>Mahome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> whoſe Principles and Doctrine tend to ſubvert the Chriſtian Faith, and to overturn both Church and State, may ſtand in their proper place; I ſay, for this end ſhall I ſubjoin their Teſtimony againſt <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> and with which I find the Church of <hi>England</hi> have great Unity, and with it I ſhall conclude this ſhort Tract, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the</hi> Quakers <hi>render the Holy Scriptures to be of no more Authority than</hi> Eſop<hi>'s</hi> Fables: <hi>That the Blood of Chriſt is no better than the Blood of another Saint; that the</hi> Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers <hi>are the Spawn of the</hi> Ranters; <hi>that the</hi> Quakers <hi>own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt is no more than a Myſtical Romance; that the Tendency of all the</hi> Quakers <hi>reaſoning about Inſtituted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is to debauch Mankind; that their Principles improved are deſtructive to all Humane Society; that their Teachers are Cheats and Impostors, and Implacable Enemies to the Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as I believe their Teſtimony herein to be Truth, ſo I do alſo hereby teſtifie and declare, that what I have wrote in my former Books, and what I have herein wrote, reſpecting their Errors, I do profeſs before God,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103405:16"/>Angels and Men, that I believe what I have wrote; nor am I conſcious to my ſelf, that I have wronged them, but am ſtill ready to meet <hi>George Whitehead</hi> upon the Terms propoſed in my <hi>Pilgrim's Progreſs from, Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keriſm to Chriſtianity,</hi> &amp;c. p. 172. and to prove my Charge therein exhibited, as well from Matter of Fact, as Argument; the former being already done at <hi>Weſt-Dercham</hi> Church in <hi>Norfolk, Dec.</hi> the 9th. 1698. in the Preſence of ſeveral Gentlemen, Juſtices of the Peace; many of the Clergy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and many Hundreds more of Perſons of Note. A Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate thereof is incerted in my Book, <hi>Quakeriſm Expoſed to Publick Cenſure,</hi> &amp;c. in the Preface.</p>
               <closer>
                  <date>
                     <hi>May</hi> 25. 1699.</date>
                  <signed>Francis Bugg.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript to the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AS it was the Manner and Way of the <hi>Quakers</hi> in the beginning, to carry out their Books to great Towns and Cities to ſpread <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> ſo have I taken ſome Pains to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe my Books, as an Antidote againſt the Growth of <hi>Quakeriſm,</hi> upon which I find their Rage increaſe againſt me, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb is, <hi>Words go before Blows:</hi> And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring what Mr. <hi>Young,</hi> an Independant Miniſter, told me and <hi>George Keith,</hi> in the Preſence of divers others, that he ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſome Diſpute with <hi>Jacob Francklyn</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Will. Penn</hi>'s Doctrine, <hi>Jacob Francklyn</hi> grew high and hot, and told him he deſerv'd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103405:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be bang'd; and ſoon after, in <hi>Moorfields,</hi> the ſaid Mr. <hi>Young</hi> was knockt down, was carried into a Houſe all bruiſed and bloody, but not robb'd, tho' both a Watch and Money in his Pocket: And <hi>George Whitehead,</hi> the laſt time I ſaw him in <hi>Jewen-ſtreet,</hi> threatned me, that God's Judgments would purſue me, and that now I write againſt I know not certainly who. And knowing 'tis dangerous fighting in the Dark, and they that can thus colour over a Quaker with the Name of a Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I have great Reaſon to fear they can procure one to murther my Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as well as my Name, and then ſay he is none of them, 'twas ſome Member of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I do therefore moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly declare, that if I come to an untimely Death, that I lay it to the Charge of the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>May</hi> the 5th. 1699.</date>
               <signed>Francis Bugg.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
